{"full_question": "1 180 g of copper is mixed with 105 g of zinc to make an alloy. The density of copper is 9 g/cm3. The density of zinc is 7 g/cm3. (a) Work out the volume of copper used in the alloy.\n(a) ................................ cm3 [2]\n (b) What is the density of the alloy?\n(b) ............................. g/cm3 [4]", "full_answer": "1 (a) 20\n2 1 AO1.1 1 AO2.3a M1 for MDV = soi Can be implied by an answer of 2\n\n(b) 178 or 8.14[…]\n4 2 AO1.3b 2 AO3.1d M1 for 15 or 105 ÷ 7 And M2 for 180 +105(20 +15)their or ‘(2+1.5)’18 + 10.5their Or M1 for some attempt to find total mass total volume"}
{"full_question": "2 (a)  (i) Solve.\n5x + 1 > x + 13\n(a)(i) ......................................... [3]\n  (ii) Write down the largest integer that satisfies 5 x - 1 < 10.\n(ii) ........................................ [1]\n (b) Solve.\n3x2 = 75\n(b) x = ...................................... [2]\n (c) Solve.\n4x + 3y = 5\n2x + 3y = 1\n(c) x = ..........................................\ny = ..........................................\n[3]", "full_answer": "2 (a) (i) x > 3 3 3 AO1.3a M1 for 4x soi M1 for 12 soi\n (ii) 2 1 1 AO1.3a\n (b) [+]5 -5 2 2 AO1.3a M1 for x^2 = 25 If zero scored SC1 for 5 seen as answer\n (c) [x =] 2 [y =] -1 3 3 AO1.3b M1 for eliminating one variable M1 for correct substitution of their x or y"}
{"full_question": "3 (a) This expression can be used to generate a sequence of numbers. n2 - n + 11 (i) Work out the first three terms of this sequence. (a)(i) ....................... ,  ...................... ,  ....................... [2] (ii) Show that this expression does not only generate prime numbers. [2] (b) Marta says odd square numbers have exactly three factors. Give one example where this is correct and another where this is not correct. In each case, write down the number and its factors. Correct 1ot correct [2]", "full_answer": "3 (a) (i) 11 13 17 2 2 AO1.3a B1 for any two correct (ii) Any multiple of 11 and its result e.g. 11th term is 121 = 112 2 1 AO1.3a 1 AO2.4a Accept any correct argument B1 at least two more evaluated terms (b) [Correct] e.g. 9 = (1, 3, 9) or 25 = (1, 5, 25) or 49 = (1, 7, 49) [Not correct] e.g. 1 = (1) or 81 = (1, 3, 9, 27, 81) 2 2 AO2.4a B1 for each Factors given must be correct for each number given for B1"}
{"full_question": "Here are the interest rates for two accounts.\nAccount A\nInterest: 3% per year compound interest.\nAccount %\nInterest: 4% for the first year, 3% for the second year and 2% for the third year.\nNo withdrawals until the end of three years.Withdrawals allowed at any time.\nDerrick has £10 000 he wants to invest.\n(a) Calculate which account would give him most money if he invests his money for 3 years.\nGive the difference in the interest to the nearest penny.\n(a) Account ................... by ................... p [5]\n(b) Explain why he might not want to use Account A.\n[1]", "full_answer": "(a)  (Account) A (by) 103[p]\n5\n3 AO1.3b\n1 AO3.1d\n1 AO3.3\nB2 for 10 927.27 and B2 for 10 926.24 or B1 for 10 400 or  10 712\nIf zero scored M1 for 1.033 oe used\nM1 for 1.04, 1.03 and 1.02 used oe\n\n(b)  He may not want to leave it there for 3 years\n1\n1 AO2.3a\nAccept any valid reason"}
{"full_question": "Lei is in a class of 28 students, 3 of whom are left-handed. There are 1250 students in the school.\n(a) Use this information to estimate how many students in the school are left-handed.\n(a) ......................... [3]\n(b) Is your solution to (a) likely to be an overestimate or an underestimate?\n Explain your reasoning.\n[1]\n(c) Vid is at a different school. He is in a class of 26 students, 6 of whom are left-handed.\nVid says to Lei\nIn our two classes there are 54 students, 9 of whom are left-handed.\nWe can use this bigger sample to improve the estimate for your school.\nWhat assumption has Vid made?\nExplain whether you think that his argument is correct.\n[2]", "full_answer": "(a) 120 to 180  \nM1 for proportion of left-handed between 71 and 101  \nM1 for their ‘1250’ × their proportion\n(b) Correct explanation for their answer, e.g. ‘underestimate because I rounded to 3 out of 30’ oe or ‘overestimate because I rounded to 4 out of 28’ oe or ‘Not possible to tell because we only have a small sample’ oe\nFT from their (a)\n(c) ‘He has assumed that the populations of the two schools have approximately the same proportion of left-handers.’ oe\nCorrect explanation for their decision, ‘Yes. This is a bigger sample so it should give a more reliable estimate.’ oe or ‘No. The two samples are from different populations, so we can’t use Vid’s class to infer properties of Lei’s school.’ oe \nB1 for identification of assumption  \nB1 for correct explanation for their decision"}
{"full_question": "7 Without using a calculator, show clearly that \\( \\sqrt[3]{4096} = 16 \\).  [2]", "full_answer": "7 \\(16 = \\sqrt[3]{64} = \\sqrt{16} = \\sqrt[3]{4096}) \\). [2]\n\nB1 for \\( 3 \\sqrt{64} \\), \\( 42 \\) or \\( 34096 \\) oe Condone \\(3 \\sqrt{64}\\) and 13(4096) for B1"}
{"full_question": "8 (a) What information from the diagrams can be used to support each of these statements?\n   (i) 7he older -ohn’s colleagues are, the lower their estimate is.\n  (ii) 0ales in the sample tend to underestimate the interval and females in the sample tend to overestimate the interval.\n (b) Comment on whether any conclusions can be drawn for the UK population from the results of this sample.", "full_answer": "6 (a) (i) [Using the scatter diagram] the points slope down/negative correlation 1\n(ii) [Using diagrams 1 and 2] 15/24 males have less than 10 so more than half under-estimate, 10/16 females have more than 10 so more than half over-estimate 2\n(b) No; it is a very small sample, so it doesn’t represent the population very well 2\nB1 for any relevant comment, e.g. small sample, more men than women, John’s work may involve estimating time so the sample is biased, etc.\nB1 for “No”"}
{"full_question": "9 Alexander, Reiner and Wim each watch a different film.\\n • Alexander’s film is thirty minutes longer than Wim’s film.\\n • Reiner’s film is twice as long as Wim’s film.\\n • Altogether the films last 390 minutes.\\n How long is each of their films?\\nAlexander’s film ........................... minutes\\nReiner’s film ........................... minutes\\nWim’s film ........................... minutes\\n[4]", "full_answer": "9 Alexander = 120 (minutes) Reiner = 180 (minutes) Wim = 90 (minutes) 4 2 AO1.3b 1 AO3.1d 1 AO3.3 M1 for any two correct expressions, e.g r = 2w, a = w + 30, a + r + w = 390 M1 for equating one variable, e.g. w + 30 + 2w + w = 390 oe A1 for solving for one variable, e.g. w = 90 oe"}
{"full_question": "11 A skills test has two sections, literacy (L) and numeracy (1). One day everyone who took the skills test passed at least one section. 88% passed the literacy section and 76% passed the numeracy section. (a) Represent this information on a Venn diagram. Show clearly the percentage in each section of the diagram. [3] (b) One person is chosen at random from all the people who took the skills test that day. What is the probability that this person (i) passed the numeracy section, given that they passed the literacy section, (b)(i) ......................................... [2] (ii) passed the literacy section, given that they passed only one section? (ii) ........................................ [2]", "full_answer": "11 (a) L N 24% 64% 12% 3 1 AO2.3a 2 AO2.3b B1 for 24% in L and B1 for 12% in N and M1 for 100 - (their '12' + their '24') in overlap Condone universal set missing (b) (i) 64/88 oe 2 2 AO1.3a M1 for 64 or 88 FT their Venn diagram (ii) 24/36 oe 2 2 AO1.3a M1 for 24 or 36 FT their Venn diagram"}
{"full_question": "Two similar pyramids A and B have surface areas 180 cm2 and 80 cm2 respectively. The volume of pyramid A is 810 cm3. Show that the volume of pyramid B is 240 cm3. [5]", "full_answer": "The area scale factor is 80/180 = 4/9 [So the length scale factor is sqrt(4/9) = 2/3] and the volume scale factor is (2/3)^3 = 8/27 So the volume of B is 810 x (8/27) = 240 cm3."}
{"full_question": "A straight line goes through the points ( p, T) and (r, V), where\n • p + 2 = r\n • T + 4 = V.\n Find the gradient of the line.", "full_answer": "1\n \n \n M1 for any correct change in change in yx M1 for –sqrp = 42  If zero scored SC1 for change in 1change in 2xy"}
{"full_question": "A unit fraction has a numerator equal to 1, for example \\( \\frac{1}{2} \\) , \\( \\frac{1}{3} \\) and \\( \\frac{1}{4} \\) . Unit fractions can be written as the sum of two different unit fractions, for example \\( \\frac{1}{2} = \\frac{1}{3} + \\frac{1}{6} \\). Write each of the following unit fractions as the sum of two different unit fractions.\n   [3]", "full_answer": "Correct solutions, e.g. \\( \\frac{1}{4} = \\frac{1}{6} + \\frac{1}{12} \\) or \\( \\frac{1}{5} = \\frac{1}{6} + \\frac{1}{30} \\) or \\( \\frac{1}{6} = \\frac{1}{7} + \\frac{1}{42} \\) \n\nB1 for each Allow any correct example, e.g. \\( \\frac{1}{4} = \\frac{1}{5} + \\frac{1}{20} \\) \\( \\frac{1}{6} = \\frac{1}{8} + \\frac{1}{24} \\)"}
{"full_question": "Simon cuts the corners off a square piece of card to leave the regular octagon shown below. O is the centre of the octagon. A and B are vertices of the octagon. OA = OB = 5 cm. Angle AOB = 45°.\n(a) (i) Work out the area of the octagon. (a)(i) ...................................... cm2 [3]", "full_answer": "(a) (i) 70.71[0678…]  3 \n1 AO1.1  \n2 AO3.1a  \nM2 for 8 x 1/2 x 5 x 5 x sin 45 or M1 for 1/2 x 5 x 5 x sin 45"}
